[Music]
hey hey
welcome back it's day number two of our
coding camp uh i'm here with my campers
again i'll let them introduce themselves
again
hi i'm bowen hi i'm keegan
hi i'm mckinley all right and we are uh
back and we're going to do some coding
activities today
uh before we get jumped into uh today
though i just want to quickly
reflect on some things we learned last
time it's a really good way to kind of
like submit some of these things in your
head
so things we learned last time so we did
avery uh with our alphabet breakfast
one thing we learned is that different
sprites have their own codes like avery
had some code
and then the apple had some code today
we're going to multiple sprites but
actually only one of them is going to
have code
other things we learned is that code
happens sequentially
so you do things in order so this is
like point towards mouse pointer move
these steps change this costume it
happens sequentially
we also use a lot of loops to make
things happen sequentially over and over
again
we learned about if statements so maybe
this thing happens maybe it doesn't but
if statements are something we use a lot
in our code
and then the last thing we learned about
was variables so last time we learned
about variables you had to create the
variable
you usually would initialize it you
would regularly modify a variable
because it's got to change if it's a
variable right and then you have to use
it somehow in your program
and so those are some skills we learned
last time and we're going to learn new
skills
this time let's show you a demo of what
we're making today
so i've got a demo solution on here that
i can show you
and so we're making a game called
hedgehog snack
so i'm going to make it full screen and
hit play
but what this is is this is a hedgehog
um and he's trying to get around the
maze
uh and you use the arrow keys to move
him around the maze
um and if you run into a wall um he he
won't go in the walls right so he just
bumps off the walls
um and then he is trying to uh get the
beetle
when he gets the beetle he chomps uh and
he says congratulations for finding the
beetle
we're also going to add a feature to our
game so this is another version of it
so almost the exact same game but in
this one we're gonna add a
timer so it's gonna be how fast can you
get the beetle
uh so you hit him um and he'll say you
found the beetle in
6.5 seconds and then your goal is to try
to be faster i was 6.5 last time do you
think i could be faster this time
come on hedgehog i was
5.7 right so that's the idea of our game
today
so let's go ahead and get started uh by
clicking on um
or go to scratch.mit.edu i'll go there
as well
and click on create up here
so we've got a blank screen we've got a
cat
on our screen the first thing that i
want to do is i want to get rid of the
cat we don't have a cat in our program
so go ahead and delete the cat for
trashcan icon here
and let's go ahead and add our hedgehog
so just like we did before
i click on choose a sprite
and the sprite that we're going to pick
is an animal
and the one i'm looking for is the
hedgehog so i'm just going to go through
here and pick the hedgehog
now yesterday i said try to use avery
walking but a bunch of my campers here
use something different anyway
i will say that if you want to use a
different sprite it'll work out okay
this time
but i'm going to use a hedgehog because
that's the way i design this game
so now we've got our hedgehog in here
our hedgehog is a certain size
as you can see the size of our hedgehog
affects how complex our maze can be
right so if you want a very simple maze
100 hedgehog work
but you can see that like about all i
could do is like maybe a u-shape if he's
so i'm going to make mine a little
smaller i'm going to make them like 50
percent
and now you can see that i could make a
more intricate maze
if i wanted to do that so pick the size
of your hedgehog
that you think is appropriate for you i
would guess somewhere like 40 to 60 type
range
the next thing i want to do is i want to
control how my hedgehog moves
so just like before if you click on
direction you can see that this hedgehog
can point uh any direction right
and so that's just how these sprites
work but what i want to do
is in this game i never want him to
point a weird direction
um and so i want to set his mode so you
can see his modes there's three modes
there's all around
there's left right um and then there's
do not rotate
so click on do not rotate um and so the
nice thing about do not rotate
is it doesn't actually matter which way
you point this arrow because he does not
rotate
um because i'm just a little ocd i'm
going to put him back to 90
but it genuinely doesn't matter where
you leave it but i like to leave mine at
90.
great so now we've got a hedgehog we've
also got to make
a drawing of the background i'm going to
put the code in for the hedgehog first
so whenever we start our code i'm going
to move the hedgehog to where i want him
to start my game
i'm going to make him start i'll make
him start in the upper left here
it doesn't really matter but i'm going
to put him in the upper left and i'm
going to start making code for my
hedgehog
so campers what's the first command that
we usually put into our code
to start things off yeah so go to events
and the way a lot of programs start is
with
when green flag clicks
and so once i click the green flag i
want to do something i want to make sure
that he snaps back to this starting
position
so to make sure that he snaps back to
the starting position that's going to be
in movement
so go to movement
and find one that says go to x
y uh so it's this one right here the
thing i really like about this command
is that if i move my hedgehog to this
position
first then the it's called the arguments
so the numbers in white here
are set to wherever i move my hedgehog
if yours
um is different numbers that's totally
fine um
they'll they'll be corresponding to
where he's at right now by the way you
can see that
because you can see his x and his wire
down here and they should match just
perfectly
the next thing i want to do is i want to
have my hedgehog do
things forever a very common thing to do
so go to control
and find the forever loop so very mean
to tell humans to do things forever
but in code it happens all the time
we're going to forever do things
so what are we going to do forever well
we're going to
listen for a user to press the up down
left and right arrow keys
and whenever they press those keys we're
going to move in that direction does
that make sense
so let's go ahead and stub out
four if statements so one
two three four
so you can see that we're going to have
four keys up down left and right
and inside of each one of these there's
a condition
and then there's code that runs if that
condition is true
a lot of conditions are inside sensing
so for this condition that's on the
inside go to sensing
and we want to know if they're pressing
a key or not
so the one that we want is this one
right here um
key space pressed so go ahead and put
this in here
now obviously you don't care about the
space bar
what you care about is a different key
that's where this little white drop down
comes into play so click on this white
drop down
and make it say up arrow so i'm going to
let you finish
the other three so go ahead and do that
same trick put a space in
for up while we've already got up down
left and right
so go ahead and finish that up all right
so i've got mine in there if you did
yours in a different order that's okay
the order doesn't actually matter
um but now we're going to put things
into them so we're going to do the same
thing we're going to do
one together then i'm going to let you
make the rest so go into motion
and we want to do two things we want to
point in a certain direction
so let's find
point uh where is it at uh point in
direction 90. there's the one
now where it says 90 this is kind of fun
uh what direction
is 90 you can actually just click on the
number 90
and it'll show you what direction it
considers 90. so 90 is apparently
straight over to the right
well if we press the up arrow i want to
go up so i want that arrow to go
up and then after i point in that
direction
i want to move 10 steps
so maybe you see the pattern already but
i'll do one more with you
so i find a point in direction 90.
i click on the 90 and i make it the
direction that the arrow says so this is
a down arrow
so i want it to be down
and then i grab a move 10 steps
so see if you can finish the other two
up for left and right
all right so i got mine in there
actually it turns out that i did the
easy two
up and down my campers had a little more
problems with uh
with left and right just people didn't
know they're left and right so left is
over that way which is negative 90 and
right is that which is positive 90.
um go ahead and try it out uh and see
how it goes so go ahead and hit your
green
uh flag button um and if you press your
down arrow it should go down
your right arrow should go right up
should go up left should go left and so
now you kind of move around
you can also kind of sort of do
diagonals if you hold down two keys at
the same time
now the speed might feel like it's just
fine right now
but that's because there's no walls in
the way this actually is kind of a fast
speed and so what we want to do is we
want to change the speed
um we're going to make it slower but
instead of just changing each one you'll
find that this is annoying so it's like
oh maybe
seven is the right number so i'd change
them all to seven you don't have to do
that right
and then you run it you're like oh
that's a little too fast maybe i want
six
and you can see how whenever you have
the same number in your code
in many different places it's better to
make a variable
that is set one time and then you can
use it everywhere else
so i go and click on variables
[Music]
and click on make a variable
and we're going to make a variable
called speed
now speed is is a different variable
than like we used last time so last time
we created it we instantiated it we
modified it we read it
this one is actually a variable called
speed that's going to be a constant
um so we're going to set it once and
we're going to use it multiple places
it can be for all sprites and that's
fine but it's actually specific to just
the hedgehog
so i'm going to click on for this sprite
only because only
the hedgehog needs to know his speed so
i'm going to click on ok
now whenever you put it in here you can
see mine says hedgehog colon speed i
actually i don't want to display it on
the screen
whenever you don't want to display a
variable on the screen just hit this
little check box beside it
so there's no need to display it on the
screen we don't really want that so we
just uncheck that
now we will need to do the the other
normal task
so we need to set my speed somewhere at
the top
so drop in this set now you'll notice it
defaulted to my variable that's not the
one i wanted
i want speed by the way if you're
annoyed about this variable called my
variable that's still around
you can this is completely optional you
can right click on it
and you can delete my variable if you
want and then it goes away because we
don't need it
so i'm going to set my speed to
something i'm going to set it to
five now the idea is
we've made the variable which is good
we've set its value
to five in this case and then the next
thing we want to do is we want to use
this variable in places
if i run the code now it won't be any
different there's nothing magic about
the word speed
i've got to actually drop this variable
in to all these places that say move
so i'm going to drag speed and i'm going
to drop it into that one
and i'm going to grab speed and drop it
into that one
i think you see the pattern go ahead and
hit the last two speed
and speed
cool so now the fun thing about this is
while i'm developing
i can try five and i can see how five
works
um and i'm actually happy enough with
five but if five wasn't good i could
change into something different let's
say i wanted four even right
so maybe i've got a really intricate
maze um and i need to like go a little
slower through it
but it's nice to do things like this
because then you can set it in only one
place
and then you can use it and all these
different things it's called avoiding
magic numbers
all right little digress there alright
so i'm pretty happy with
our hedgehog i think what i really want
to do next is i want to get into drawing
so i'm going to hop over to the solution
just kind of see it again
you can see that what we have to do here
is we have to draw a maze
for our hedgehog to go around to get to
his goal so the way i drew this maze
there's many ways to draw it
is i made a solid like dark brown
that filled up the whole screen so it's
actually a rectangle it's solid it's
dark brown
maybe i'll just go in and look at it
here so it's a solid dark brown
rectangle that feels little screen
and then i drew a series of light brown
rectangles
um on top of it to kind of like make the
path
there's many ways to draw but that's
going to be the strategy that we're
going to use together
so go ahead and do this for me let's
draw our background so the first thing
you have to do is you have to click over
here where it says backdrops
and a backdrop just like sprites i can
have code
if you want and then this tab right here
called backdrops this is where we're
going to be doing our modifying
he can also have sounds by the way we
don't care about sounds for him but we
do want backdrops
now before what we did is we just used a
built-in image
but this time we're going to draw uh
from scratch ourselves
drawing um it's like i don't know
there's there's like a peppa pig episode
where like she gets glitter but as soon
as like kids get glitter they just go
crazy with that
somehow it just goes nuts drawing can be
the same way so make sure you have
patience with your little ones um but
what we want to do is we want to do some
drawing
let's get you familiar with the drawing
editor um it's really powerful to get
good at drawing
it's kind of like where steam comes in
it's a combination of art
and science but you do have to get good
at your tools so you can see that
there's a number of different tools
the one we're going to focus on today is
the rectangle tool
and then the select tool so these are
the only two that we care about today
so the first thing i want to do is i
want to draw a big rectangle on here
for that dark brown color that fills up
the whole screen
so what i do is i click on fill color
mine defaulted to purple for some reason
and i'm going to try to find uh the
color that i want for my brown
their system uses something called um
color saturation brightness
which i think might be a little
confusing for kids uh but but you'll get
used to it but you
you pick what color the rainbow you want
first um then you pick like
how uh you know like intense you want it
to be the saturation
and then you pick the brightness so i'm
going to make mine kind of like a brown
the outline i actually don't want an
outline
so i'm going to click on this little
like red line and this means
don't give me an outline at all right so
it's like transparent it's like it's not
there
so now i'm ready to draw so what i want
to do is i want to draw a rectangle
that's just big enough it does not have
to be perfect to fill the whole screen
what they've decided to do in scratch is
that this white box
this is your screen and anything you
draw like outside of your screen doesn't
really matter
so i'm just going to make it big enough
to go beyond my screen
you can see what i'm doing here is after
you draw a rectangle you
um go into a mode where you've selected
that rectangle and you can modify it
which is kind of neat so i can now
modify it by grabbing these handles
that's something that they added by the
way there's also what's called bitmap
mode
we don't want that we want to be able to
modify our rectangles after we put them
on
so that's my big background color the
next thing i want to do is i want to
click off of that rectangle
so by the way if you use the select tool
you can click on it
and you can see these blue lines around
it or you can click off of it
if you click on it you're going to
modify it if you click off of it you're
going to draw something new
so i'm going to draw some more
rectangles uh so for mine i'm just going
to use
maybe like a lighter brown for his path
and i'm going to start drawing
rectangles so i'm going to draw a
rectangle that kind of comes
down and then what i choose to do is i
kind of like click off of it so it's no
longer selected
and then i'm going to draw a rectangle
uh so it's not a very good rectangle
draw a rectangle that comes like over
this way
um and you can choose to make your maze
as complex or as simple
as you would like right just make sure
that you can in fact get through your
rectangle um
or else your your game is going to not
be playable the other nice thing is if
you decide like oh this is kind of too
low i'm going to
move this up you could always move
things up afterwards so i'm not going to
tell you what to draw
it's completely up to you but you can
make it as
simple or as complex as you like um i
don't know why but i felt like making
mine a little bit more complex this time
was that a good plan i'm not sure um
but i chose to make mine kind of complex
and so you're going to pick
like where is the end goal of your
of your maze so for mine my end goal is
going to be up here at the top
so i'll make that a little bigger there
so i'm going to eventually put my beetle
up here you can also be ocd about
getting the edges to line up
it's like this edge is just a little bit
low there and i can try to get that
just perfect on there and the nice thing
about this tool
is that you can always modify things uh
after the fact
so i think that that is probably good
enough um
maybe i'll move that up just a little
and i'll call mine done
so pause the video and spend as long as
you need
uh to draw a maze do keep in mind
that your hedgehog has to be able to go
through it um
so what i'm going to do really quick is
i'm going to take my hedgehog now so i'm
actually just going to click on him over
here
and i'm going to make sure that he fits
everywhere so he kind of sort of fits
through there
does he fit through here yeah he kind of
sort of mostly fits does he fit through
here
yeah so make sure you can just drag your
hedgehog around
and make sure he fits through your whole
maze mine's just a little bit on the
tight side
so instead of 50 big i'm going to make
him 40 big
all right so pause the video get your
hedgehog together
and i'm going to come around i'm going
to see how my kiddos did with their maze
drawings
all right neely you're up first uh so
neila drew a maze
um let's see what kind of maze you drew
nila tell us about it nila where's your
where's your
victory point gonna be [ __ ] mostly
helped me with it
yeah and that's my factory and you're
gonna go up there great
all right bowen what's your theme oh no
hedgehogs in this one all right what do
you got
underwater they're trying to be friends
watch
so they're trying to be friends so
you're going to try to bring them around
and
make them be friends
yeah normally don't yeah don't octopus
normally eat jellyfish bowen
but this time they're trying to be
friends all right mckinley will do yours
next
oh we got a spiral thing going on here
so what what are your creatures
uh mine is an owl and a mouse
the mouth is actually bigger than the
album
and so i was gonna eat it uh and keegan
oh man yours is very elaborate what uh
what's your uh what's your plan here
keegan so you've got like a dog
um going through a very elaborate red
maze so keegan chose to do one that's
very elaborate it looks really cool
buddy
um but he's gonna finish it later uh
because it was kind of taking a while
um i love it are you excited about your
maze are you guys
excited about your mazes uh-huh all
right
so uh we've got our backgrounds ready to
go
and we're ready to add some more code
so first off go ahead and play your game
um and actually this is a fix i'm gonna
have to make my starting spot wasn't
quite right for my hedgehog
so i'm going to actually adjust my
starting spot so you can see how he
accidentally starts on the wall
whoops so i'm going to fix that so what
i'm going to do is i'm going to move him
over to here
so i want him to actually start right
here so that was a little change
now i've got two options i can either
change these numbers so like it says 186
there
so i could just change it or i could
bring in that command again
either way would work so i'm going to
change mine to match like what it says
there so it says 186 159
uh hopefully you planned to head better
than me and you don't need to move your
hedgehog
but for me i had to do a little movement
so now i can see that i'm going to try
to get around my maze
and everything's going to be good so the
thing that i want to fix next personally
is i don't like that i can just go right
through the walls right like this is
going to make my game
really easy if i can go just right
through the walls just zipping through
there
so let's write some code to stop that
from happening
so find the bottom of your code mine's
getting kind of long
and let's add another if statement if
statements are in control
and here's an if statement right here
now what we want to do with this if
statement is we want to see
if we're touching the wall right
so um touching is something that's in
sensing
and the way we know if we're touching
the wall or not is through this
touching color so grab a touching color
and drop it into your if statement
now how do we get this color this color
has to be exactly right so there's like
literally millions of different shades
of colors so i want the color to be
exactly right so you can click on this
and you could try to like select the
color but let me assure you
it would be hopeless completely hopeless
that's where this eyedropper comes in
so you're going to click on this
eyedropper and it immediately kind of
changes your screen a little bit
and the idea is it wants you to hover
your mouse somewhere over your
background that's why it's like an
eyedropper of the background
and what you want to do is you want to
pick one of your walls um
and it'll change to be that color and
then you just click
right and so what that did for you which
is super easy
is it picked exactly that shade um off
by a little bit in the shade won't work
at all
by the way that's a good reminder make
sure that your walls are exactly the
same color right you can't have
variations
because it'll only detect that shade so
if you're touching that color
what do we want to do um well if i could
stand up and still bring the camera so
imagine that i'm walking and i hit the
wall
then what i would do is i would do this
and if you think about describing words
uh
what happened there so i hit the wall
and then bone what did i do next can you
figure it out
yeah so i turned around and bounced off
that's exactly correct way to go bo
so those are both motions so
how do i turn around um so i can see
there's a turn
15 degrees and i put this in here
and it doesn't matter if you do turn
left or turn right so i hit the wall
and i turn around now this might be a
question for keegan
um keegan how many degrees is it if i
turn
completely the opposite direction do you
know how many degrees that is
180 you got it so you're going to do a
180 way to go bud
um and then we're gonna jump off the
wall some amount
now what i'd like to do is i'd like to
drop in another move 10
and when i hit the wall i'm going to
choose to bounce off
more than just one um speed amount
i'm going to bounce off double what my
speed is
does that make sense so so if we were to
hit and turn we want to jump off
twice what our speed is so how do you do
twice your speed
so you need an operator and so we want
to take speed and multiply it by two so
you've got to find the operator which is
for multiplication it looks like this
it's a little star and drop it in here
by the way you'll notice that it's
always outlines it in white when you can
drop it
but what i want to put in here is i want
to move two
times speed and speeds in my variables
so if i hit the wall i want to turn a
and then i want to move off two speed
amounts right and that's just
just so you bounce off quite a bit right
uh let's try it
so we're going to hit the uh the green
flag button and then now
when you hit a wall what should happen
is it should just kind of like
jump you off of it so you can like try
to go through it
but it shouldn't let you right so it
should stop you before you go through
the holes
so test a few of your walls and make
sure that you can bounce off of them
you also notice that i don't have
anything on the bottom here so i can
kind of like go down into the bottom
maybe i considered that a feature or
maybe i didn't think about it i can kind
of go off to the side some
but overall i'd say that mine's working
and i'm happy with it
if you made your maze too tight
somewhere this is probably where you're
going to figure it out
so if you've got a spot in your maze
that you can't go through oh i did
something crazy there
yikes i'm not going to worry about that
if you found a spot that you can't get
through or something that's just too
tight
you can go into your maze and fix it oh
i discovered a bug in my game if i if i
go at a diagonal i can go through walls
all right um that was an unexpected
feature so don't use diagonals
all right so i think mine's going pretty
good um what i want to do is i like
sounds right so like when i hit a wall i
like to have some kind of like small
sound now there's a lot of sounds that
are built in
and we could use one of those but i want
to use it as an opportunity to show you
something new
so down here in the lower left there's
like this ad
extensions thing click on add extensions
and there's actually a lot of additional
code extensions that you can add
some connect to robots and some do neat
things the one we want now is music so
go ahead and click on music
and when you add an extension what it'll
do is it'll basically just kind of like
add a new category
to the bottom of your toolbox so there's
a bunch of these
that you can add this one is is music
and so what i want to do is i want to
add a play drum
so whenever i hit the wall i want to
play a drum
you can pick between a snare drum or a
bass drum or all kinds of drums
i think i feel like a conglomerate drum
right now for no real reason
what should happen now is whenever i run
my game
when i hit the wall
it should play a little sound right so
add a little sound to your game
um and if you're not happy with one you
pick you can always try another one
uh the next thing i want to do is
actually save my game because i have not
saved it at all yet
so you can type in whatever you want i'm
going to call mine
hedgehog snack because he's going to eat
something here in a second
and then like i say it automatically
saves so you don't have to hit
anything for saved but you can hit file
save now if you'd like and then it gives
you that like warm fuzzy feeling
that you've got it saved all right the
next thing i want to do
is i want to have something that's my
goal my
target the thing i'm trying to get to
since i'm a hedgehog and i want a snack
i want something a hedgehog might eat
so i'm going to go into choose a sprite
here so go ahead and click on the circle
down here for choose a sprite
and i'm going to choose that a hedgehog
might like to eat beetles
um so i'm going to select the beetle um
obviously you can pick anything you'd
like but i'm going to pick up beetle
i'm going to make my beetle kind of
appropriately sized
and put him into the maze at the
location where i want him to go
now to be honest my beetle is a pretty
simple sprite
he doesn't move he doesn't have any code
at all
we're just going to detect if we hit him
or not
and if we hit him that's how we know we
won the game so he's just about the
easiest sprite you could possibly have
but you do see that there's no code here
go back to your hedgehog
and all your code will reappear so the
next thing i want to do is i want an
if statement to see if i'm touching my
beetle
um so we've done if statements a few
times go to control
i drag out an if statement by the way
one thing to be careful of bowen did
this for me as an example
is he accidentally put the if statement
like inside of another if statement
that's bad don't do that right
so make sure it's inside the forever
loop but all your if statements
like none of them should be like inside
of the other one so you can always kind
of like see
that they're all independent if
statements and that's important
and if your code's freaking out that may
be something that you have wrong
so this last one so if some condition
then do this
it's going to be a sensing condition
again
instead of a color we're going to say if
touching
mouse pointer but obviously we don't
want mouse pointer we want beetle
so if we're touching the beetle then we
want to
to win the game so we want to win the
game there
when i win the game what i want to do is
a couple things first i want to make
some sounds
let's see what sounds my hedgehog has
he's got
pop i don't want pop pop doesn't sound
like i'm eating a beetle
so i want to add a sound so just to
recap i went into hedgehog
i went into sounds and then down here
i'm going to click on
choose a sound and i think the sound
that i would recommend for you is
chomp the easiest way i think to find it
is to start typing it
and then to add chomp and so if you play
chomp
um we actually use that with apple if
you remember
now chomp sounds okay but i would rather
repeat
chomp four times and i'm going to do
that in my code right
so as soon as i hit the beetle i want to
chomp four times
so i'm going to go to control
and i'm going to add a repeat loop
to go four times
and what i want to do four times is i
want to chomp until
done so play sound chomp until done
so i'm going to try this out and then it
sounds like i need to help my campers
out some
so i'm going to go ahead and move around
i'm trying not to use diagonals because
i discovered diagonals are bad which i
learned just now
um and then as soon as i get to my
beetle what should happen
um it goes forever right so it kind of
sort of almost worked
um the thing that didn't work is it just
kept doing it forever and ever and ever
so i'm going to fix this one thing and
then i'll help my campers
so the last thing i want to do to fix it
is i want the game to end
after i start chopping them to end the
game go to control
go to stop all and then put it on the
bottom of your repeat floor
and then things should things should
work better so as you play your game i'm
going to cheat here and go diagonally
through my wall
which i discovered i could do only
recently
and so it chomps one two three four
times and then the game ends
see if you can get that working in your
code and i'll help my campers do the
same
all right so i think mine's going pretty
good uh one bug uh that mckinley had
which was kind of interesting
um her uh target um just so happened to
have the same color
as her walls so when she like almost hit
her target it bounced him off
if that does happen to you just draw a
different color kind of on the outside
of it and it'll it'll fix that bug so
you might have that it's kind of a weird
bug
that'll affect some people uh let's go
ahead and add one more feature
the feature that i want to add is a
timer um a timer is a very special type
of variable
because it's built in um and so if you
go to motion
there's a built-in timer uh in here
which is kind of interesting
um so i've got to scroll around oh it's
not it's not a motion it's in sensing
um there's a built-in timer um and so
this timer
starts when your game starts um and
i like to go ahead and like do that
explicitly so when my game starts
i want to reset the timer so what i'm
going to do is i'm going to take reset
timer and put it in here
to make sure that it zeros out when the
game starts
and then what i want to do is i want to
say what my time was
at the end so scroll down to the end
here
and so i'm going to go chomp chomp chomp
but before i say stop all i want to say
something i want to say
either time so go into looks
i put on a say hello for two seconds
um and then what i want to do is i want
to say like your time was
uh and then the timer um since i want to
do kind of like two things i want to say
like your time was and then also
i do the timer i've gotta put those
together
uh with a join command once you see it
it'll make sense so instead of just
saying a single thing i'm gonna say
join i'm gonna say your time
was and then
what i'm going to say is i'm going to
grab that timer from out of sensing
so your time was and then it's just
going to say a number
and you can phrase it however you want
you can say your time was
or you could just say time or you could
you can make it whatever you want you
could also put multiple of these joins
together and put it in the middle of
your sentence
knock yourself out right i'm going to
keep it simple and i'm just going to say
say and i'm going to join the word time
and timer for two seconds
so now whenever i run it my game starts
um and so i can run around i can do my
game
uh and when i finish uh it says my
time was 12 uh something
now some little tweaks so the things i
didn't like these are little tweaks
i would like for it to save my time for
a little longer maybe five seconds
just so i can read it so i can register
whether it's better than previous or not
another thing i don't like is i don't
like that when i click the green flag
my timer starts me right away because
i've got to click the green flag and i
got to move my hand over to the arrow
keys
so just just to fix that this is a
little fix
i'm going to say something just to kind
of like pause the game a little bit
so i'm going to go into looks i'm going
to drag say hello for 2 seconds
and i'm going to put it just before i
reset the timer
and it's just going to say ready or
maybe get ready
whatever you want so now if i hit the
green flag it says get ready and it
gives me a second to move my hands over
and now i can start uh trying to get to
my goal
i hit the wall a couple times so this is
not going to be my best ever
and then i get to it chomp chomp chomp
11.25 so you can play your game as many
times as you want
[Music]
and you can try to see if you can get an
optimum time
and then of course you want to have your
parent play it
uh and see what they can do so mine that
time
was oh 10.4 a little bit better
all right so a little feature there uh
with like getting you ready it's kind of
like a get ready set go
um and then a little feature down here
uh
for the for the timer all right so i'm
gonna
uh go around and i'm gonna see how my
campers did i'm also gonna click this
share button
and the share button gives me a url that
i could share with other people
in order to be able to share remember
you have to have a logged in as an
account and you have to verify your
email address
all right campers you're ready for me to
see what you made all right neela you're
up first let's see what you've got
so it says get ready um and then you're
going to take your hedgehog around your
maze
um your your game is very difficult
because of all those diagonals isn't it
so you kind of work your way down
you're doing great babe neil made it
past the hard spot
i had to edit a little bit there because
it took just a little bit yours is
challenging neil get the bread and we'll
see what your time was
your time was oh yeah 38 seconds
great job neela give us the vist there
all right bone let's see it hit go
i'll save your green flag bowen
all right so bowen says get ready uh and
he's got this octopus theme
uh so he's going around he's trying to
get the jellyfish
now the jellyfish to be clear is not
going to get eaten by the octopus the
jellyfish and the octopus are friends
cool looks great you got a time of 15.2
great job bone did you have fun making
this game great job
we'll go with [ __ ] next so sissy's got
uh the owl theme and as mentioned she
has a black
uh wall and her mouse had black on it so
she had to like outline it in red or
something
all right so she's playing her game
where are you at session i don't even
see oh
her her owl is teeny tiny um she is
playing
it's just the world's smallest owl and
this al
books it around the course so it's a
super spiral
it's minnie albers mega mouse
and so you got it in 23 seconds great
job sis great creativity
all right keegan let's see yours hit the
green flag
um get ready so he's got a super dog
that is not the right path super dog
so he's got a super dog running around
his red maze
is this dog man is that who this is no
way
go the right way
i want a bark sound effect 24057
all right great job everybody everybody
have fun yes
yes yeah cool uh so i'll go and say a
couple things uh just to wrap it up uh
so the the learning things from today
coding is fun uh you can do this that's
kind of our message every day
um art and science like this drawing
things
really are important to make your games
custom and make uh you own it
and your creativity uh you can see just
from my campers here is really what
makes this
uh things interesting a few more things
in here but i won't worry about those
i look forward to seeing you tomorrow i
will start another coding adventure
see you then bye
[Music]
i didn't know you could do that
apparently if you do it
if you go at a diagonal you just go
right to the wall
neither bob nor i tried diagonals i
didn't even think about diagonals until
needles mate by the way i had to make
this
if it bothered you that if you hold down
two keys at the same time that you
actually can
sometimes walk through walls oh this is
where now i can't even do it
but oh there we go i got through if it
bothers you about the diagonals um
one one way you can fix it this is not
required at all
is really there's this code right here
so there's this if statement right here
that's asking if you're touching the
color um well here's what i'm going to
do to fix it this is completely optional
you just watch me
is i really want to take this code and
separate it by itself
and i want to call this code after every
move
and a good way to do this this is a
great way to introduce like functions
um functions in scratch are called
blocks
you can just watch this you don't have
to do it but if i make a function called
check for the wall which is not really a
great name for a function but that's my
name for the function
so this code right here is the function
check for the wall
and now i can put that in everywhere
after move speed and now what will
happen is i've made that function that i
can reuse you can see i used it four
times
and now it shouldn't let me go through
the wall so even if i'm like down here
and i hold down both keys to go to
diagonal
i just can't get through there right so
you do not have to add that
is not a requirement maybe the next time
i film this i'll put it in there
but it is a great time to show you
functions um and functions or whenever
you're gonna have the same code in
multiple places here i've got it in
four different places and you can see
how i broke that out
and it fixed this bug uh going through
the wall all right
that little edition it just bugged my
family so i thought i'd show you how to
fix it if it
happened to bother you all right thanks
for joining us bye